Okay, maybe we shall get started. Um,
this is the second uh of the post-
training lectures. We're going to talk
about the exciting developments in RLVR
or reinforcement learning from
verifiable rewards. Um, and I think this
is uh in some ways very timely. Um I
didn't get to update the slide but there
was just a kind of announcement you know
by open AI folks that they had solved uh
one of the kind of major herdish
problems. Um so that's a you know open
math problem using one of their like
thinking models. How does that thing
work? That's exactly this you know
thinking model stuff or RLVR stuff. And
so thus far you know where we're at is
we are kind of at the left side here
right after we finished last lecture.
We've got kind of instruction tuning.
We've got RLHF. We got some good stuff.
That's chat GPG. And what remains is
kind of the modern developments in
thinking models. Uh these abil the model
ability to do very long coot and solve
these hard verifiable problems like
mathematics uh and coding in some cases
as well. Um and remember that I ended
last lecture with kind of this uh little
bit of a downer note. the RLHF wasn't
really going to get us where we wanted
to go because of this problem called
overoptimization. Right? So, we're going
to go and collect a bunch of preference
data. Preference data is very useful. Uh
we will build some reward model and then
we will RL against that reward model.
But this thing is fundamentally very
annotation bottlenecked, right? Because
we have a reward model and you can't
keep putting compute into the same
reward model. Eventually, you're going
to overfit your reward model. Um, and no
matter how good of a job you do at
regularizing, you know, eventually
you're going to run into this this
problem with overfitting. Um, and so
really this is very depressing and it's
not really the the potential of
reinforcement learning. If you're a big
reinforcement learning believer, you
know, you're going to look at all sorts
of things like Alph Go and so on where
you say, well, in these domains, you
know, RL really did an amazing job. um
what is the difference between what
we're doing in RHF and what you know has
been achieved in these more RL native or
RL natural domains um and really the the
difference I would say or one major
difference between something like Alph
Go and something like RHF is that in
Alph Go we are optimizing exactly what
we want right like you get the win- loss
conditions of the game of go you don't
have any sort of like sloppiness to that
definition and so you can just put in as
much compute as you want and as long as
the objective improves, you're doing
well, right? Um, in some sense, these
are search problems, whereas the top one
is much more of a learning problem. Not
quite a a precise distinction, but
that's one way of thinking about it. So,
now there might be other domains like
formal mathematics or even natural
language mathematics that have this
flavor of being more verifiable and
therefore much more amendable to
reinforcement learning. So, that's going
to be kind of the motivation for why
we're going to study some of these. and
the algorithms aren't going to be that
different fundamentally, but where we
will end up will actually be
surprisingly different. Um, and so the
lecture is going to be in two parts
today. This kind of mirrors a lot of how
we've structured the course in other
parts. Um, so in the first part of the
lecture, I'm going to talk about the
core algorithms. This is like basic
knowledge for you all. You will use some
of this for your assignments. Um, and so
I'm going to talk about things like what
is gpo, like how does PO work? And then
after I've done that, I'm going to dig
through a bunch of uh open source
releases and show you how what I've
taught you in the first part sort of
reflects in the technical reports of
many of these uh major open- source
model releases. Okay,
so we're going to dive in to the methods
and like sort of basic section. Um and
the first thing that I'm going to start
with is PO, right? Like we can't really
discuss RL uh for language models
without discussing PO. Um and even
though we've done it once, PO is
confusing enough that I think you will
benefit from doing it twice, right? Um
the most important thing to identity
let's say to remember in RL for language
modeling is policy gradients and in in
particular kind of this like reinforce
gradient trick, right? Um what we are
always going to be doing is gradient
descent on our rewards and we are going
to do so by taking essentially weighted
uh SFT updates where the weights might
be positive or negative. We will define
what R is but this equation is important
because it will reappear throughout this
lecture. This is in some sense the core
from which everything else is derived.
Now you know building upon that remember
that the intuition from last lecture was
we want to take more than one step at a
time. A policy gradient requires us to
sample from our policy every time we
want to take a gradient step. Can we
reuse our rollouts? Well, you can do
TRPO, you can do PO, and so on and so
forth, right? Um, I'll talk about PO in
a minute, and I've already talked about
TRPO. I won't really get too much into
this. If you've taken an RL course, PO
is of course, you know, well understood
to you, like you understand this
algorithm. Um, but I don't assume that
all of you have taken an RL class and or
understand, you know, RL. Um and so PO
in case you're not familiar, you know,
is a kind of real workhorse um of RL.
It's been used in a variety of very
difficult RL settings. Um OpenAI has
done quite a few of these in their early
early days of being, you know, very RL
pill. Um they had, you know, this was
the I think OpenAI gym. Um where they
were talking about the PO algorithm and
they're like, hey, we can get these
these uh people to walk around using
reinforcement learning. And a much more
dramatic demonstration of this was their
open AI bot which they trained using PO.
Um, and so this can excel with kind of
deep RL and like highdimensional action
uh in state spaces where it's much more
complicated to do RL than it is usually.
Um, oh yeah, and there's there's you
know the the open AI man running around.
All right. Um, so at a conceptual level,
PO is actually very simple, right?
Remember that I um told you, you know, a
important part of all of this is getting
rid of PO. That's been a motivating
factor for a lot of people. But if you
look at the pseudo code of PO, you know,
this is from uh, you know, the OpenAI is
like spinning up on RL documentation.
You look at this and you say this is not
that bad. This is actually like pretty
easy. I could implement this in one go.
You sample some trajectories. I compute
something called an an advantage using
any method of advantage estimation. I
clip the advantage in this like kind of
slightly strange but okay way and then I
update the policy under this clipped
advantage and that's fine right and then
I can fit something called a value
function as well okay fine this is all
relatively easy looking in practice um
and so I think because of this you know
people are like ah it's okay po's
totally fine but then you see blog posts
that look like this and this should
strike fear into your heart right
because if you see a blog post that says
the 37 implementation details of PP EPO,
you know that this is an algorithm that
is very sensitive to your implementation
decisions, right? Um, and you know,
there's all sorts of things that you can
do and all sorts of different libraries
and implementations and they give
totally different numbers based on which
ones you use. Um, and it turns out that,
you know, many people have implemented
this wrong. And so there's papers saying
like actually the baselines that some
people use in PPOs aren't even baselines
at all. They fundamentally change the
optimization problem. Um and so you know
basically because of this I think I
would you know not be able to get
through the rest of the lecture without
telling you well we actually maybe need
to start looking at some implementations
of PO and the implementations of PO let
me tell you for language models are not
particularly pleasant. Um you know this
is a I mean a very good representative
slide. If anything this is a very good
description of what PO looks like. You
know you've got uh advantage estimation.
this big block in the middle. That's
this advantage thing. You've got an
experience buffer because you're going
to keep some of the old stuff. It's
going to be training this value model
and the value models you be being used
in the advantage estimation calculation.
Notice how the the green box appears
twice. Um, and importantly, you know,
some parts of my objective, the KL term
actually operates token by token. So,
it's not actually just a bandit problem.
It's like a whole multi-step RL problem.
And this is all very difficult and
complicated. Um and so this has led to a
variety of you know really tricky
implementation things that you have to
do. And if you look at a variety of
implementations you know you find often
that there are things that people do for
PO that are a little bit strange uh and
tricky at times. Um let me see if I can
find um you know so uh one of my
students implemented PO for a project a
while back doing RLHF right so PO if you
remember was used in RHF and so you know
we had this nice robust reference
implementation of PO um and it took a
long time to get working so I like
looked into the details like what did we
actually do to get this thing to work
the outer loop is fine the outer loop is
something like you go through your
rollouts and you're going to take some
PO steps you're going to compute some
loss and clip some gradients and take
some steps right totally reasonable
outer loop Um but then you start kind of
looking into it. Um for now the the
actual like inner compute loss part
follows almost exactly the PO update. So
this also looks mostly good. We're
computing things like you know the
advantages and you know we're computing
the clipping ratios and then we're
updating the model based on that. So
this is all kind of good but then you
kind of get to some of the messier
parts. Um actually I'll skip the
rollouts. um where you have things like
well maybe we need KL penalties to sort
of you know keep the original model
close to the reference but actually this
only works if you clip the KL off at
zero which of course if you know
anything about KL divergences that
totally ruins the point of a KL
divergence right you have both positive
and negative values being summed um if
you remove this blows up immediately
right all sorts of things like this can
happen this is not to say that this is
the way you should implement PO if you
were doing it I think the reason why I
bring this up is to say implement
mentations for RL algorithms can be
somewhat tricky and somewhat sensitive
because of all the moving pieces in PO
and because of the high variance in the
gradient estimates like these are all
very very tricky things um that are
happening and you know another thing
that you often see this one is not just
our implementation it's very common um
in the original PO paper you have this
thing called a generalized advantage
estimator that's basically looking at
this like um you know gamma discounted
reward where you have this value
function that's estimating the reward at
every token generation step. Um, but it
turns out that, you know, people often
just use gamma equals lambda equals 1,
which is just a degenerate setting that
turns this back into a bandit problem.
So, you've kind of thrown away a lot of
the structure that you get from uh PO.
And so, like if you run this algorithm,
you know, after a bunch of engineering,
you will get what you expect. Then you
know when you run your your RL
algorithms for the assignment you should
expect to see similar things like the
rewards go up the reward model rewards
go up if you're doing RHF and then the
negative KL regularizers kind of go
down. This is a reasonable thing to
expect to see. But anyway, you know the
the point of all this is to say
implementation of PO can be quite
painful depending on the environment. It
can require hacks to stabilize. All of
this is kind of painful. Not to say that
it's not possible. Lots of people have
trained very good models on PO. Um, many
of the labs have sort of very turnkey
solutions for getting POS to to work at
scale. So, this is not impossible. But
for people like researchers who are, you
know, implementing this from scratch, PO
can just be really finicky and
complicated. Another reason why PO is
disfavored in many cases is that
requires a value model to estimate kind
of the value at each token as you go. Um
and how big is the value model? Well,
it's you know as big as the original
model. So this consumes some memory that
you would rather be using for other
stuff like you know models or inference
uh servers. So now you might say well in
last lecture you told us about this DPO
thing and DPO seems pretty good. Um why
don't we just use DPO for everything?
Well the problem is DPO is a very
specific solution to a very specific
problem. DPO is good for pair-wise
feedback in the form of Bradley Perry
comparisons. that is very specific,
right? Um, and if I want to solve math
problems, you know, my math problems
don't come in the form of inherently
pair-wise comparisons. There are other
DPO variants that are designed to sort
of break that pair wise structure, but
really you're just kind of using the
wrong hammer for the job, right? You do
not want to use DPO necessarily for what
you would normally use PO for. PO is the
more general hammer that you can hit
kind of everything with. um DPO is
generally offline although I think this
this uh distinction is very overstated
because it can be made online by just
iterating DPO repeatedly. So I don't
think this is necessarily a big
difference. Okay, so that's the context
for you know uh all of this. Um and then
so you know that similarly to DPO
there's just an enormous desire by the
research community to not have to use PO
right um hopefully the fact that you
know DPO and GRPO have gotten adoption
tells you how painful it was to get this
to work in many cases um and so GRPO
much like DPO is the alternative it is
the simpler way to do RL for verifiable
task has taken over for the most part um
RLVR in the open-source you know open
knowledge let's call it uh community um
and it is very very similar to PO and
spirit. It just strips out a couple of
the most complicated parts and by doing
so um allows us to have a much simpler
algorithm. So GRPO is by um uh a
Deepseek paper um I think it was their
like deepseek math paper um where you
start with PO right it conceptually it
says PO is a good idea but we want to
change just a few things and what does
it change it changes it's arguably the
most complicated and annoying part of PO
which is the value function right so the
value function is the thing that you
subtract as a baseline to reduce
variance of your gradient updates um the
value function is a whole neural network
it destabilizes training we don't want
the value network. So what do we do?
Well, we get rid of the value network,
but we still need an advantage. I don't
want to do reinforce vanilla reinforce
because the variance of that is going to
be really, really high. So instead, what
we're going to do is I'm going to
compute advantage as a zcore within a
group. And I'll explain what that means
in a moment. But basically, the idea is
kind of the following. Normally, you
kind of look at a reward that you get.
And if you had a value function, you
would compare it to your your predicted
value. You would say my neural network
says I should have gotten a score of
five. I got a score of six. So this is a
good roll out. Right? That's usually
what you do. Instead, what you would do
is you would get let's say your your
roll out with a score of five. You would
now sample 10 other rollouts and you
would say how good was I compared to my
10 other rollouts, right? If I'm doing
better than my mean, then I have a high
advantage, right? In some ways, a very
natural way of computing advantage uh in
context where you can multiple sample
from the same prompt or something like
that. Um so GRPO is exactly this idea.
If you look at the the you know initial
definition of GRPO that appeared in the
Deepseek paper you know you see this is
the uh uh the objective that's being
optimized. They're going to do exactly
the PO update where they have this like
min clipped advantage plus a KL term to
keep you yourself close to the
reference. Um and then KL is computed in
a particular way that detail is not
particularly important. And importantly,
this advantage is computed as a zcore
over samples of a group of outputs O of
one through O of G. Right? So that's uh
or within each group you have oh sorry
this advantage of I this is the place
where you compute the advantage. What
you do is you take the reward over your
rollouts within each group you subtract
the mean and you divide by the standard
deviation. Right? So you get a zcore for
each group. Um so uh in the online case
and this is an important distinction
because in many cases you may actually
end up running this online rather than
offline. Um in the online case the
clipping right just kind of disappears
because the ratio between pi theta old
and pi theta is one. This clipping
operator never does anything. Um and you
just get min a of i a of i. So this is
just advantage minus a kl penalty.
Right? So I'm going to do rl on my
advantage which is defined by this. So
in the online rollout case, it is a very
very simple object uh that kind of uh
makes sense as a RL uh target. So I can
pause here for a moment in case any of
the conceptual bits of gRP are not
clear. I mean in some sense this is a
foundation of all the exciting uh math
stuff or you know you can replicate all
the exciting math stuff using gRPO. So
it's worth understanding in a little bit
of detail before we sort of move on to
to some of the nitty-gritty details.
Okay, good. Simple enough that everyone
understands in one go. I will take it.
Um, and gpo is very very simple. Um, you
know, because of the lack of value
function, you can basically write down
kind of all of gRPO in a very simple
block of code where you just say I'm
going to roll out, you know, k times.
I'm going to compare my, you know,
observed roll out to those K sort of
references, Zcore it, and then just take
a reinforced gradient against those
weights, right? Um, so you will write
this in your assignment. Um, and it's
going to involve a very simple set of
steps. You know, compute a reward for
each of your K rollouts. You know,
normalize your rollouts, compute the KL
term, um, and then just take gradient
updates on the combination of your KL
term and these rollouts. um you'll have
to do a little bit of thinking because
in order to do this using um autodiff
you will have to do a stop grad
somewhere but it's actually not that
complicated and you can sort of see that
you can do a onepage implementation uh
of this uh basic idea right um and this
is a reference implementation of gRPO
that I took um from you know some some
folks at McGill which has a really nice
little toy version of this whole thing
um and the computation of the group
indices and like the standard devi ation
calculation and all of this just kind of
fits in one half of a slide. Um, the
only thing that they do differently than
like the literal paper write up of GRPO
here is they add a little tiny 1g4 to
the standard deviation calculation to
prevent it from blowing up when you only
have a single sample or if your samples
happen to have the exact same rewards,
right? Which which does happen if you're
in a domain where you can get exactly
numerically zero rewards, like you
failed to solve a math problem. Um but
hopefully this um you know emphasizes to
you kind of how straightforward gpo is
and why almost all open- source work has
been built on this algorithm. It's easy
to implement, easy to understand. Um and
if you as we'll see in the results, it
provides fairly compelling results in
terms of uh emulating a lot of what the
the closed source labs have done using
potentially bo.
Okay. So how well does it work? um in
the original uh Deepseek math paper,
which if you're into sort of math AI
stuff, I would encourage you to read.
It's a it's a nice and really
interesting set of results. Um you know,
they show that GRPO uh the yellow and
the blue lines does much better than
RFP, like rejection fine-tuning. You'll
implement this as a baseline as well.
That's just taking the correct answers
that your model generates and training
on them and throwing away everything
else, right?
um and they seem to show process
supervision which is grading not just
the final answer but grading the
intermediates give you some gains. I'll
talk more about that later. That is an
important thing to uh discuss and cover
because that's one of the big sort of
design decisions uh for these kinds of
RL problems. But for now, you know, you
can just internalize the fact that GRPO
works. The blue and yellow lines are
above the others.
Okay. Um so now let's think a little bit
more about the GRPO objective like what
is happening in this objective are we
actually taking policy gradients there
are important conceptual questions uh
that we should really think through um
and so if we think about the difference
between GRPO and PO right remember that
PO had this value function thing which
feeds into the advantage and in GRPO we
stripped that out and we replace that
with the zcore guy right this a of i
ratio of r minus mean divided by
standard deviation
So, is this a good advantage? Right? I
think for those of you that have been in
an RL class, you kind of already know
the answer to this question. Like, is
this a good advantage function? Um, you
know, why what makes a good advantage or
what makes a valid advantage function?
Well, you know, if you look at Senardo,
you know, the the big kind of classic
book for reinforcement learning, you
know, they will say, well, there's this
algorithm called reinforce with
baseline. And the things you're allowed
to do is that you know if you're doing
policy gradients right which is this
this line over here this very first
equation right I want to take my
gradient step on the direction of my
rewards and the thing you can do is you
can take your rewards and I can subtract
any what they call state dependent
baseline in this case our state if we're
in the bandit world is just the prompt
right so you can have a prompt dependent
baseline that you can subtract and
anything that does just this is a valid
form of a policy gradient. So you're
still going to descend in the same
direction as long as you do this. And
depending on your choice of B, you will
either have lower or higher variance um
in in doing this gradient descent
process. Now you should probably notice
that what we're doing is not this,
right? We are not just subtracting a
constant value. We're also dividing by
the standard deviation. Um and so that
is kind of a problem it turns out.
Well, it's in some ways a problem, in
other ways it's not. Right? If you
really want a conceptually clear
algorithm that really does what's like
written on the tin, like it actually
descends the reward, GRPO does not do
that. Right? Because as I've highlighted
in red here, right, GRPO divides by the
standard deviation, which breaks sort of
this kind of, you know, baseline
contract. We're not just dividing or
sorry, subtracting a baseline, we're
also normalizing by the standard
deviation uh of my rewards. Um you could
of course oh there's another thing uh
that GRPO does which I didn't mention
earlier um as an implementation detail
that is kind of tricky which is GRPO
does this kind of almost per token right
so they'll divide by the total length of
the sequence um as a normalization
factor but if you sort of try to derive
gpo from first principles following the
policy gradient and baseline theorems
you'll end up with something different
you won't have a length normalizer and
you won't have the standard deviation
normalization, right? Um and some folks,
you know, soon after GRPO came out
noticed this. Um and they wrote a paper
basically saying, well, if you don't,
you know, do these like two things that
are different, then you get very
different potentially very positive
behavior. I will talk about that, you
know, um also when we get to the uh not
open AI, sorry, uh Deepseek R1 uh paper.
Okay, but the main thing here is to say,
you know, GRPO is not the first
principles derivation of this idea. It
is actually doing something slightly
different with both pros and cons.
So what are these two terms doing? We
now know that GRPO is not actually
directly descending on the reward
objective. Um, we know that it has these
two correction factors. What do they do?
Well, the length normalization is easier
to see, right? So what are we doing? we
are dividing you know longer sequences
with a bigger number and so what this
will do is that it's going to encourage
the model to generate long outputs right
because or sorry when you're wrong it
will encourage you to generate wrong
outputs um because let's say I'm I know
that I'm going to get a math proof wrong
I'm going to incur my negative reward of
let's say negative one I'm just going to
generate an infinitely long string if I
do that I'll get to divide by infinity
um and I'll get to totally get rid of my
negative penalty right That's a that's
an extreme case, but you kind of
understand that if you divide by the
output, you encourage the model to blab
on once it realizes that it cannot
actually solve the problem. Right? So
this is a length problem that you'll end
up getting. Um if you fix that, um
you'll find that often you know what
people have observed in GRPO of like you
know coot like chain of thought thinking
length growing and growing and growing
that actually turns out to just cap off
at a constant rather than just
continually and forever grow. So this
seems like a potentially good thing. Um
and especially on the incorrect cases,
you really don't want to be, you know,
generating longer and longer and longer
um outputs. Um so the standard deviation
normalization, this one's a little bit
more complicated, but if you think about
it, what I'm doing is I'm dividing by
the standard deviation. And so this can
be thought of as emphasizing problems
where the standard deviation is small,
right? And when is my standard deviation
small for a binary reward problem? Well,
that's when the problems are too easy or
too hard, right? If my problem is really
easy and I get 100% all the time, I'm
going to divide by one over or you know
the the number the I'm going to divide
by basically zero, right? Because
there's zero variation if I always get a
question correct. Similarly, if I always
get a question wrong, I have zero
variation in my rewards. You know, I'm
going to upweight that significantly,
right? So the standard deviation term is
upweing sort of the two sides both easy
and hard questions. That seems like
clearly a thing that maybe we don't want
because we want our models to
potentially learn on kind of things that
are within its solvability range.
Okay, so that's kind of the algorithmic
components um of RLVR and I'm going to
go through um several of the different
recent model releases and kind of talk
through all of the algorithmic
components um that I think are quite
important um including um some of the
stuff that I added this year that's new
which is really the agentic stuff that I
think has been catching on and is
increasingly important uh for using and
deploying uh these models. But before I
do that, I can pause here and if anyone
has algorithmic questions, I'll I'll
take them before I move on.
Okay, good.
All right, so we're going to start with
DeepSeek R1 because I think this is, you
know, you know, a bit of a social
phenomenon. I think everyone should
know, you know, a bunch about Deepseek
R1. I think it's a lovely paper. Um,
kicked off the wave of open-source uh
RLVR models. Um, and what's remarkable
about it, I think it was really the
first uh thing to have matched OpenAI
01's sort of behavior, right? So, the
key things about OpenAI1 was you have
very long chains of thought. It's, you
know, clearly RL um and you have really
good performance on hard math problems,
right? Um, and they also provided a RL
recipe that anyone could do. And I think
from the perspective of R&D, this is
very important, right? If your solution
was like you have this horrible PO thing
that no one but deep sea can run um then
that is much less of an impact um at
least for us researchers than this like
kind of GRPO thing which anyone can
really uh play with even you in sort of
your assignments and finally they have
some really interesting sort of
distillation insights that I think you
know have held up um you know even even
now okay so the starting point of
deepseek R1 and I think you can kind of
see how a lot of deepseek's like
expertise build on each So, you know,
they had this deepseek math paper where
they were doing gpo. They had already
understood a lot of the nuances of
rlinging on math problems. Um, and so
because of this, you know, they started
off with a lot of the components of
deepseek math. Um, but one of the really
important differences, um, and I'll sort
of highlight an expert just because I
think it's particularly important is
they abandon process supervision, which
was the thing that worked really well in
deepseek math and they go only with
outcome supervision. And just to be
clear, outcome supervision is when you
have reward only for whether the final
answer is correct or incorrect. And
process supervision is when you have a
grading rubric, let's say, to check
this, uh, validity of intermediate steps
in a proof. Um, a lot of people thought
process supervision was important.
Turned out it wasn't critical for a lot
of things. So um R1 was interesting um
in that it has a lot of different
components but one of the very
interesting components um is R10 where
they don't really do that much post-
training. So they have a base model. Of
course the base model as we all know now
is is also mid-trained. And so this guy
can can do some amount of instruction
following. And then on top of this base
model they do you know basically RLVR
where the rewards for their GRPO
algorithm is accuracy rewards for
whether they correctly solve a
collection of math problems. Um and
format rewards. And this one's important
because the format rewards basically
allow them to strip out the chain of
thought later. They want the model to
properly use thinking tags to enclose
their coot. Um, but this is a very
simple recipe. GRPO is very simple.
Accuracy rewards are very simple. Um, in
fact, you will implement and replicate
essentially this set of results in some
ways. Um, and you do just this very
simple recipe and where do you end up?
Well, you end up something that is only
a little bit worse than OpenAI 01.
Right? So this is really really really
clean and I like this result because it
has none of the messes of like a real
production post-training pipeline thrown
in. You don't you know really question
whether like oh was it because of the
RHF helping or this or that. It's a very
simple base model plus GRPO. Your math
abilities are quite good. Um and I think
R1 also kind of took off partially
because of the interesting phenomena
they claim to have observed in the
paper. So one of the things they claim
to have observed is you know as we go
longer and longer and longer during
training the model is able to think for
longer and longer and longer the coots
get longer and longer and longer. Um and
they also highlighted this thing that I
I believe went viral on social media
which is like ah the aha moment where
the model is like you know if you train
it for enough it coot is able to do
things like oh there's an aha moment
that I can flag here. Um and you know
they thought this was really
interesting. Um it is unclear to me
whether either of these phenomena are
really particularly uh impressive in
many ways. like we now know that longer
coots is arguably a a natural side
effect of the length normalization of
the gpo algorithm and the aha moment um
you know others have showed um is
actually the appears in even the base
model and so clearly it can't just be a
result of the RL algorithm right like
you know lots of people say aha I can
use this as part of solving the math
problem the model has learned it during
pre-training you know it's not
surprising at all that somehow during RL
just happens to get extracted because
it's you know emitting a lot of math
tokens right um so I think the phenomena
that was highlighted is not particularly
salient or or exciting but I do think R1
was a really important milestone in that
it highlighted just how simple RLVR
could be right this is very in some
sense clean as an algorithm and as a way
of solving these really difficult
problems um and so R10 was this very
nice, clean, controlled setting. And
then uh R1 was their attempt to kind of
productionize this system. And I think
one thing that's nice about R1 and and
I'll show you the Quinn uh equivalent
later is you can kind of see how you
kind of stack all the pieces together,
right? I think in we've studied all the
pieces in isolation. Like we know where
pre-training is, we know that there's
RHF, we know SFT, but how do we compose
all the pieces to actually get a system
at the end? Um well usually the thing
that you do is something like well we
have our mid-trained model we're going
to do a bunch of reasoning training
maybe some long context extension
somewhere too and then we're going to do
RLHF at the end because that's in some
sense the most userfacing object right
like we want to make sure that the
formatting and all this is nice RLHF can
very much help with that process um one
of the other things that they did was um
they added a language consistency reward
for the chain of thought for their
production model um I think If I
remember the report right, this was
because um the R10 style training
without a consistency reward would like
kind of language switch in coot and they
thought this was like very
uninterpretable and slightly disturbing
and so they wanted to just have it
output a single consistent language and
so they do this just for sort of
interpretability uh reasons. Um, and
then they have some of the
non-verifiable rewards as well, uh,
thrown in to GRPO almost as kind of
blending into the RLHF process, but
otherwise it's a very very similar thing
and the whole pipeline I think is very
straightforward. Um, so for SFT, what
they kind of do is pretty simple. So in
R10, they don't want to do any SFT at
all, but in R1, they're willing to do
long coot data. And you know, when
you're reading these open source tech
reports, it's kind of fun to try to read
between the lines. When they say
something like, "We construct and
collect a small amount of long coot
data." You know, you might wonder, I
wonder if that was distilled from some
other models. You know, not that that is
a particularly like negative thing for
open source models. Um, everyone is
nowadays doing this, but I, you know, I
just kind of find it funny that it's
like very carefully written. You know,
collect a small amount of long coot
data. Um, and so this is used to
fine-tune the model. We know that for a
very good base model just SFT on long
coot can unlock a lot of 01 style
capabilities. Um and you know that's a
great starting point for RL. So they
they start there and then they add some
verification to filter out these coots.
Um and then they you know continue on
with with uh processing. Um and you know
I think many papers since then um some
including some some from my students
have shown things that you know if you
have the right kind of distillation
procedure and you have the right kinds
of base model you can basically get a
lot of the long coot sort of reasoning
juice just from SFT right and I think
this is maybe interesting because one of
the things that I think is is still an
open question is like do you really need
RL for some of this and I think maybe
one way of thinking about the role of RL
in language modeling is that RL RL is a
great source of supervision, right? Like
if you're solving frontier math
problems, you just don't have the
supervision to get detailed long coots.
And RL allows you to self-generate that.
But once someone has generated these
long coots, you could potentially also
learn um from imitation. And that seems
to be kind of what a lot of these like
distillation results uh partially show.
Okay. Um so the RL part for R1 is
basically the same as R10. Um minus the
language consistency loss that I
mentioned. It's basically just we run
the RL training using gRPO. Um, and you
know that leads to essentially the final
phase which is what we learned about
last lecture. So we do some basic
instruction tuning style SFT. Um, and
then RLHF. Um, for non-verifiable tasks,
they basically use the same thing as uh,
Deepseek V3. So there's really no
surprises uh, at all here. How well does
it work? You know, it's kind of really
really good, right? Um, and I think this
is the reason why there was all that
kind of panic or like big uh sort of
noticing of DeepSeek because R1 was
genuinely a very good model, you know,
like it beat 01 on many of the of the
categories. Like it it matched a lot of
the test time scaling behavior that
people expected. Um, and it came from a
very simple recipe. So, you know, it was
very easy to understand where the gains
uh were coming from.
Um, and the last thing related to some
of the distillation discussions that
that I was saying is you could then take
R1's coots and you could put it into
Quent 2.5 and if you did so you could
really significantly boost the
performance of these models like in some
cases sort of matching a lot of these uh
specialized thinking models and so in
other words you know really if you can
get the right kinds of long coots that
are legible to these models um often it
is possible to get them to to reason for
for long periods of time like the base
models are already uh surprisingly good
and this works even for llama models um
as well which I I think is quite uh
fascinating.
Okay, so to close out kind of the um uh
sort of deepseek saga um I quite like a
lot of the deepseek tech reports because
they often do both ablations and they
also tell you failed things that didn't
work. Um, and if you've been following,
you know, what they've been doing,
Deepseek Math has this all this like
process reward model stuff. It's like we
got to verify all the steps and then you
read R1 and you say like where did the
process reward models go? Well, they
tell you where the process reward models
go, which is we tried to to get process
reward models to work. They just didn't
do very much for us. It turns out that,
you know, um, outcome reward models are
great and they're good enough and you
can scale the data for those a lot
better. Um, I think a big debate for
PRMs was where are you going to get
these like step-by-step rubrics, right?
And it's very hard to scale that up. Um,
I think at this point it's quite clear
now that outcome reward models are very
very good and that's kind of the bulk of
where the action is happening. Um,
similarly if you know you were kind of
around for the initial 01 release a lot
of people speculated about what was
going on inside OpenAI's01. They were
like oh are they doing PRMs? are they
doing tree search like Alph Go, right?
Um, you know, they too tried a lot of
MCTS and they sort of describe we
couldn't get it to work very well. Um, I
just very much want to highlight and
sort of like the fact that they're very
open about all these explorations and
the things that they tried and didn't
work. Um, rather than to say like, you
know, they didn't try it at all. Cool.
All right. Um and you know if I talk
about um actually I'll pause here in
case anyone has questions although I
don't know if yeah
explain
more
because I guess you said for like
>> yeah so the question was like for
positive cases what does the length
normalizer do and of course in those
cases the length normalizer like
encourage enourages you to shorten the
coot. Um, which is good if you want to
save on inference cost. It's bad if that
degrades your accuracy. Um, but I think
the main issue is that for for the long
uh for the negative ones like you get
like some really long responses. In the
positive cases, it can't shrink it that
much because there's a lower bound to
how small your coot can go, you know, to
solve a particular problem.
>> Right? I guess I'm trying to understand
that explanation for the uh for for the
diagram.
>> Yeah, I think Dr. GRPO has a cleaner
diagram of this. So like you know in the
in the R1 diagram, this is all
aggregated. This is like all the you
know responses across their evals. It's
not just the positive ones. Um but uh if
we look at the doctor gpo plot over
here. Um so this is like the average
output length and this is the incorrect
output length, right? And so you you
kind of see that and the correct output
length is here, right? So um you kind of
see somewhat that like this is really
being driven by the incorrect ones as as
we kind of would expect from the
explanation. So the the story at least
in the these sets of controlled
comparisons is is quite clean and clear.
Yeah.
Cool. Um
so now I'm also going to talk about an
alternative method um Kimmy K1.5 or
alternative uh paper and approach. Um
and I always feel like when I talk about
R1 I als I'm obligated to talk about
Kimmy K1.5 because they kind of came out
the same time as R1. They also beat 01.
And yet everyone is, you know, all about
DeepSk. And Kimmy is not quite as often
brought up in the conversation, even
though their models are extremely good.
And I'm not just sort of talking about
them out of pity, per se. Um, I think
Kimmy has this nice thing that they do
something some sets of things quite
differently um than Deepseek. And we can
learn quite a bit from like the fact
that both of these work, right? I think
this is kind of part of the theme of
this class which is by reading all of
these tech reports and by looking at
broader patterns we can roughly start to
understand what are kind of the the
valid or easy spaces to to get these
algorithms to work. So um they do
actually quite a bit more detail in
talking about the data set construction
and like curriculum generation for the
RL process which many have said is quite
important. Um, and they also have a
different RL algorithm which in some
ways like has similar intuitions but is
not exactly GRPO. And so this is another
nice validation that technically
speaking um I don't think you
necessarily need something like GRPO to
get these guys um to work.
Okay. Um so the first part I want to
talk about is the data. Um the data
remains very important um for all of
these processes. Um and for RL there's
an additional wrinkle of kind of
curriculum like what kinds of
difficulties of problems do you want to
throw in right in SF you don't really
think about difficulty very much because
you just sort of jam the data in there
right like for whatever data that you
want you just do pre-training losses and
the model is forced to learn from these
in SF there's a little bit more of a
subtlety we talked quite a bit about
sort of the hallucination issues and
maybe sometimes you don't want to train
on some of this data um but for RL
there's this additional wrinkle that if
your problems are too hard, you get no
rewards, right? And if you get no
rewards, you have no signal. And if you
have no signal, you can't learn. So it's
very important to kind of have broad
coverage of the right kinds uh of
examples. Um and so what uh the Kimmy
folks do is first of all, they like try
to get a whole big broad range of
coverage of data. Unsurprising. Um they
exclude multiple choice because that's
kind of covered in lots of different
domains. They want things that require
long deep thought and their argument is
maybe multiple choice doesn't have that.
But maybe this last one I think is maybe
the most important idea. This appears in
a lot of different uh RL papers, right?
You basically filter all the examples
for things that uh sort of either pass
um or or sorry you filter them based on
a best of K filter. So here um you take
examples um and if they succeed on best
of eight like if you sample eight times
and the model can do it at least once
then that's not a great RL example
because it's kind of already at the edge
of the model's capabilities right you're
not going to teach it anything
particularly new and so you only look at
examples that you know uh uh basically
fail this test um because that allows us
to essentially um pick the right kinds
of of problems s and so this saves
compute. Um it allows you to sort of
skip problems entirely. Um you can also
sort of filter on both sides to get
problems that are neither too hard nor
too easy. I think the general consensus
in the research community is that doing
this kind of like medium range
difficulty filtering is very good if
really what you want is for RL to like
progress at a steady pace. Um, you know,
as with DeepSeek, no description about
SFT. We can speculate about what that
is, but we have no concrete information.
Um, so I think the interesting thing
about Kimmy is that they have a DPO
inspired argument, but they end up
actually in a place that's very similar
as uh GRPO. And I think the fact that
they end up in similar places is
suggestive of which of these components
are are potentially useful. uh if you're
designing a new URL algorithm for
example. So they start at the exact same
place as everyone else right so this
should now look like very familiar to
all of you it's just you know maximize
the expected reward under my policy and
I've got this KL regularizer on the
right that sort of keeps me close to uh
my base policy or maybe even the
previous iterations policy depending on
how you're going to do this uh do this
RL. So they're going to follow the same
DPO style derivation where they say
assume that I can maximize analytically
and I solve for the reward model that
does that maximization or corresponding
to that maximization and that's going to
give me this like ratio of policies um
and I'm going to plug that back in to my
objective up there um and try to solve
for what is happening. Well, what
they're kind of now saying is they want
to try to match the reward model. Um,
and for this equality to be they want
this equality to be true, which is true
at the minimizer. And therefore, this is
a big heristic. You know, if something's
equal at the minimizer, why don't we
just put a squared loss on that thing
and minimize the squared loss? Um, I
think optimization people looking at
this would be horrified at this. But I
think this is a totally reasonable
intuition in some ways, right? We know
that these two things should be close uh
when the model is good. So it is also
maybe okay to treat making those two
ceilings explicitly close as a
surrogate. Um the this derivation as you
can see is very very different from gRPO
right we're not going through the PO
path to derive this uh this uh update
but now actually lo and behold you take
a gradient of this L you end up with
something that looks surprisingly like
uh GRPO with an added regularizer term
right what you end up with is this thing
that is a policy gradient with a
baseline RB bar um and that R bar is
actually the mean of each sort of
condition these X's um and you have this
additional regularizer term uh which is
essentially the KL term that would
appear in GRPO. So in some sense, you
know, we've reinvented the group mean
normalized baseline um through quite
different means.
Um and so, you know, the the Kimmy
folks, I think, in some ways, had a a
nicer or or better view uh of the length
problem. I think the GRPO folks were
like, "Isn't it great that the length is
growing uncontrollably? I'm sure our
model is being smarter." Right? That's a
little bit of an uncharitable take, but
like when you present this plot as a
positive thing, the implied statement is
like it's great that our model is
thinking for longer. Um, but the Kimmy
folks kind of look at this like long
coot problem and they say, well, you
know, if we're making long coots,
potentially that's very wasteful, right?
Like we don't really want long coots
because coots cost inference, right? So
they not only not not only do they not
have a length problem because if you
look at this objective they don't
normalize by sequence length um but they
actually want to go even further and
they want to compress the length of the
response and this is another sort of
important sort of feature that we kind
of see generally occurring in language
model development like we want the coots
to be as short as possible we want to
solve hard problems we want don't want
to think for very long because when we
think for very long we have to kind of
you know essentially subsidize the user
If you're OpenAI and your users have um
uh the $200 pro plan and your models are
thinking for like an hour at a time,
that's not a very good place to be in,
right? Whereas if your models are
thinking for 5 minutes at a time, that
is a great place to be in. Um and so for
all these reasons, um Kimmy wants to go
and compress the coots. How do you do
that? Well, you know, the simplest RL
thing to do is you come up with a sort
of heristic uh length reward um and you
just tack it on to the uh to the uh RL
process. This reward is surprisingly
complicated. Um and the thing that
they're doing is you're trying to make
longer sequences shorter and shorter. Um
correct answers also should be short. Um
the interesting sort of balance here is
if you make the incorrect answers too
short, they no longer have a way to
recover, right? It's like so let me give
you an example. Like imagine uh I'm bad
at geometry, right? Like I'm a I'm a AI.
I'm bad at geometry. I get lots of
incorrect answers and the penalty makes
my geometry coots really short. Right
now my geometry coots are zero. I'm
really bad at geometry. I will never
recover from this. Right? I will never
get a positive geometry reward ever
again. And I'm stuck. And so what you do
is you don't sort of force the incorrect
answers to be super short. Um you
incentivize them to be just a little bit
shorter than sort of the average, right?
So that the the incorrect stuff doesn't
grow unboundedly. Um and so this has
like uh in in the end like a
surprisingly reasonable set of outcomes.
Um and so as I said before, you know,
they have a really nice sort of RL set
of views on how they do their their data
set curation. So not only do they have
this data set that they filtered, they
also look at the success rates of how
often they're able to solve particular
problems. And once a model masters a
particular problem, it gets taken out of
the problem set. So you save some
compute doing that. I think basically
everyone doing RL does these kinds of
like uh success rate filtering to avoid
both wasting compute or uh working on
problems that are way too hard uh for
the model. Um and they you know
basically have uh rewards that for code
they take ground solutions and they
generate some new test cases and for
math they actually have a reward model
to check for answer equivalence checks
and you know this is a really funny
thing in some ways because we started
out this lecture by saying you know we
want to work on like you know formal
math or something something truly
verifiable right where where you can a
compiler can check the correctness of
your math and then we've like gone
through like most of the lecture And
then in the end, where have we ended up?
Well, we ended up with a reward model. A
reward model that checks the correctness
of math answers. Um, once again, you'll
you'll kind of see why in uh the
assignment, or maybe if you play with
the assignment, you'll see why. Um,
you'll quickly find out that answer
equivalence checking is a very difficult
problem. Um, because in math, you can
like write, you know, equivalent things
in many ways. And not only that, a
language model can give the answer back
in many ways. Even if you prompt it to
say give the answer back in like latte
boxed, maybe sometimes it skips the
boxed, maybe add some extra stuff to the
box, right? There are lots of ways that
the model can just fail to get the right
answer by a strict correctness checker
even though it has the right idea. And
so for these reasons, basically, you
know, most RL sort of projects have a
very complicated like answer checker,
either a reg x or a model or who knows
what in order to avoid these kinds of
problems. It's a real like rabbit hole
um getting like the verified part of
RLVR right.
Cool. Um the last thing which you know
connects to some of the the systems bits
uh that we had talked about earlier and
the inference bits is RL uh optimization
and RL infra is really quite hard. Um
you know training is hard and inference
is hard and RL puts the two together. So
in some ways no wonder is it really
horrible and difficult. Um, even worse,
I think one of the things that you don't
initially appreciate about, you know,
how hard it is to make RL efficient is
kind of think of the following scenario.
Now, imagine, you know, you've got your
rollouts, but you've got one really hard
math problem, like let's say, like, you
know, one of them is like the Remon
hypothesis, and your model's like really
chugging along on the remon hypothesis.
It's got this gigantic coot, right? Now,
what's happening in the meantime? And if
you're doing naive inference, everyone
else is waiting on this one roll out to
complete in order to sort of move on to
the next phase, right? So if you're
doing these batch things, long rollouts
can really hurt you. Um, and so you
know, RL really needs to deal with all
of these sort of like really tricky
low-level details. Um, so you need to
deal with the fact that some coots can
get really long. Do you need to truncate
them? Do you somehow like set them into
a different machine? Who knows, right?
These are all decisions that you can
make. Um, if you switch from training to
rollouts, like you roll out once and
then you train and you roll out and you
train, you have to somehow, you know,
deal with this. Either some of your
machines are pure rollout machines and
some of them are in uh uh training
machines or you're like switching out
frameworks all the time. Both of them
are very costly. Um, and then finally,
you have this really difficult and
horrible trade-off, which is on policy
stuff is mathematically and training
dynamics wise very nice, right? So GRPO
in its simple on policy form behaves
very nicely. You will experience this in
your assignments and then you will get
kind of greedy. You will say ah but my
systems utilization is so low, right? I
could do so much better if only I could
reuse my rollouts. Then I can overlap my
inference and computation and do all
sorts of clever things. And so you will
attempt to reuse these rollouts. and
that will lead to off policy problems
which then lead to de uh destabilizing
your training and all sorts of things
that are very difficult. Um so you know
these are all sorts of things that end
up getting very very tricky. Um and so I
think most open-source uh technical
reports will have these days a section
talking about their RL infra. Um, and
their RL infra, you know, is going to
have to have, you know, both a training
part, that's the blue boxes over here,
and an inference part, which is the
green part on the right. Um, and you're
going to have to move weights from the
training part to the inference part. So,
you need some sort of story for how to
move those around. Um, and you need to
coordinate them closely. And in some
cases, maybe they even share the same
machines because as inference is
running, the training one might be idle,
right? So all of these are kind of
complexities and you have lots of very
complicated uh systems things to do. Um
so we already know uh that uh Kimmy
beats openio1. Um but we also see some
really nice things showing that like as
RL proceeds you're able to think longer
and performance goes up. But in some
cases it's not that we're just
unboundedly increasing tokens. You know
we end up getting cases where I think
omni math is a good example. you're not
thinking for that much longer, but your
performance continues to go up. So maybe
this is a good uh example of sort of
this length control kicking in and doing
good things.
Um the final thing I want to talk about
is you know you might wonder is this
actual RL stuff much better than just
training on you know correct answers?
You know this is called expert
iteration. It worked very well in a
number of past papers. um in cases where
you're dealing with very unstable stuff,
you may actually want to do expert
iteration instead. Um you know, Kimmy K1
has very large scale ablations showing
that um uh these kinds of RL methods uh
work consistently better than expert
iteration. So that's the orange beating
the blue over here. So you can't really
avoid RL if you want to squeeze out uh
all of your performance.
Okay, I can I can pause here in case
anyone has questions about the Kimmy
stuff and then I'll uh move on to the
the last of the three which is uh Quen
3.
Great. Okay. Um so the last one that I
want to talk about is Quen 3 and uh also
Quen 3.5 Next Coder. The names are
getting complicated. Um and Quen 3 is
later but they have actually really
interesting scaling and data results. So
I want to talk about those. Um and the
successor to this which is Quen 3.5 Next
Coder um is interesting because it I
think has the most details of I would
say like Asentic RLVR training out of
the the major tech reports. Um and they
do you know lots of lots of cool things.
Okay. So once again as with Deepseek uh
one of the nice things that we see with
kind of the Quen report is the full way
that all of these are organized. And
this is very similar to the deepseek
structure, right? Um we do base model to
to basically SFT then reasoning RL um
and then they have this like thinking
mode fusion. I'll talk about that later.
And then they do RLHF and then they have
a model that gets shipped. But of course
they don't want to serve that directly.
So they do distillation to get their
smaller models. Right? I mean you know
Quen 3 is is quite a respectable open-
source model. You can basically have
this be your mental picture of how, you
know, frontierish uh language models are
built, you know, putting all the
components together and I think you
would have a pretty reasonable picture
of what is happening, right?
Um and Quinn uses basically the at this
point tried and tested playbook for
RLVR. Um I think they take lots of the
best parts of Kimmy and and Deepseek and
they sort of get it right. Um they do a
lot of filtering for difficulty because
we know that saves compute. that's a
good way to get, you know, good data.
Um, they also do other things like, you
know, they remove things that the model
can get right without coot because we
know that's not a thinking problem. Um,
they remove things that are too similar
to validation data to try to
decontaminate things. Um, and then they
sort of do a little bit of manual
filtering on sort of reference coots. Um
maybe most remarkably about Quen 3 is
they actually do their RL on very few
examples, just 4,000 examples. Um but
once again, if you kind of have the rest
of the pipeline right, you can actually
get surprisingly far. Um so the core of
the RLVR components are maybe not super
surprising because they are really, you
know, building off of uh DeepSeek uh R1
and also Kimmy. Um there are some
interesting Quen 3 specific things um
some of which you know they've ended up
like getting rid of but I think some of
the ideas are actually quite
interesting. Um so one of the things
that they do um is they mix sort of
thinking and non-thinking things with
tags. Um and that's kind of how they end
up having a thinking mode where you know
the model has a long coot and they can
mix that with a non-thinking mode. So
both the instant response model and the
long coot model basically live in the
same model and this was not true uh in
many cases you know like there was a
often a thinking mode and a non-thinking
model uh even at open AI they also have
uh I thought this was quite interesting
um which is they have this like way of
early exiting thinking where if they
append the special string they'll
immediately stop the coot and the model
is forced to give an answer to whatever
you know prompt is given um we see this
even in in sort of we see this
affordance in interfaces like chatgpt
where you're able to like terminate the
thinking early and try to get an
immediate answer uh for example but what
we see with this and I've always thought
this was a a kind of surprising and
interesting thing which is that as you
vary the thinking budget doing like kind
of this early termination trick um you
end up finding that the performance of
the model kind of degrades gracefully
like even though you at the lower
thinking budgets, these models are kind
of getting truncated mid-thought.
They're able to give surprisingly
reasonable uh responses um even at that
point. And we see that, you know,
consistently even with very small
thinking budgets, the thinking mode
models are much better on all these sort
of like mathematical or coding tasks uh
compared to uh the sort of instant
response mode which is much more of like
the classic instruction following plus
uh RHF models.
Um and so you can then you know one of
the nice things they do for us is look
at the contribution of all the different
components to performance. And in many
ways this is not something that should
surprise you too much. Um you know if
you do sort of this this uh you know
reasoning RL and then general RL you're
able to slowly get improvements um in
all the different sort of tasks you know
things like arena hard or counterfact
QA. These are general tasks for which
you know you want more normal RLHF and
we see significant boosts to that
performance across the board. Um there
are some degradations that we see in
sort of math and coding because we fuse
together non-thinking uh components but
the degradation is not so bad. I think
actually you know even though these
numbers in an absolute sense are small
um in later releases I think in some of
the quen 3.5s um they've gone back on
fusing both thinking and non-thinking
into a single model um I think what they
used to they used to call this hybrid
models because they found this kind of
drop uh kind of unacceptable they wanted
to squeeze out all the juice possible on
thinking modes and so they've now I
think separated uh these models from
each other
okay um the very last uh topic and paper
uh that I want to cover um is Quen 3 oh
sorry I flipped the two it's coder next
not next coder um which is one of the
newer uh models to come out and I think
if you're interested in like you know
general agent stuff of course there's
other agents things to think about like
hardnesses but if you're interested in
like how do you actually build an agent
um this is probably a good report to go
read clen coder next great sort of agent
post-training uh paper Um
but in some ways post training for an
agent is not very different from from
everything that we've described. It's
not like there's a new like agent
training algorithm. Um really um you
should internalize this lesson
throughout the entire class. Data is the
important thing, right? So if you're
going to train an agent or like post
train for an agent, what are you going
to do? You're going to get the data
together, right? So there's two parts to
the data, you know, for to get a lot of
the capabilities. You can't just inject
them at the end. like you have to
probably start a little bit earlier. And
so there's an extensive mid-training
phase that happens to try to get as much
coding and sort of agent-like
capabilities into the model as possible.
Um so they'll do things like they'll
take repositories and concatenate the
files in the repository to generate
these very long context data and put it
into the model. Right? We know that the
model is eventually going to see these
very long coot traces where maybe the
agent has opened a bunch of files very
useful sort of pre-trading style data.
They take pull requests um and then they
try to construct like synthetic context
for it using rag that is potentially
helpful for understanding the pull
request. That all goes in mid-training.
um they will take documents that they
detect using an automated method to have
text and code and then they'll use an
LLM to transform this to a nice markdown
format. Throw that all in as well. Um
and then finally they're going to have a
language model you know uh talk about
coding on web documents that are coding
related to generate sort of codingish
synthetic data. Um, and then they'll
take publicly available coding agents,
run them on various environments, which
I'll describe later, and the traces of
those runs all go into mid-raining. Um,
they'll do some fairly standard stuff as
well like instruction following, and
they'll have an additional task, which I
think is not super relevant um, for us
um, for filling in the middle. Like if
you're coding and you want to fill in
the middle of a span, you know, it's
useful to have that ability. So they
they throw some of that data into
mid-training. Um, but otherwise, you
know, this is a very uh standard but
kind of in-depth data collection
procedure to try to get some of these
agentic abilities uh into mid-training.
And then the Quinn folks do something
that I don't know if I've seen before.
It's actually quite interesting. Um,
they'll take the mid-trained Quen 3 Next
model um, and they are actually just
going to train a whole bunch of
different expert models for different
kinds of coding adjacent tasks. um and
they will end up with four different uh
you know agent experts and then they're
just going to distill them all back into
the same model. Um I can only speculate
as to why they do this. I don't think
I've seen it in other works. The closest
one I know of is DeepSeek V3 or was it
V3? V3.5 sorry Deepseek V3.5
um or it's 3.2 maybe 3.2 sorry 3.2 I
think uh did this thing where they have
different experts whose only job it is
to sort of format and process data. So
they have data processing experts which
generate the data for the full training.
But I don't think I've seen this thing
of uh generating different model experts
and then distilling them back. That's
actually closer to like some academic
work like branch train merge um and so
on. Those are definitely things people
do. I haven't seen it much in frontier
model training. That said, each of these
experts is actually kind of interesting
and what they do is they basically do,
you know, full-on RL or andor SFT
training on a whole bunch of different
subtasks that they've like defined. So,
they have a webdev expert where they SFT
on valid web code based on different
kinds of checks. They'll do things like
build UX experts uh trained on many
different tool formats. Um, and they'll
have QA. So the QA agent is just you
know trained on more uh synthetic data
for code. Um but then maybe the most
interesting for us and the most involved
is kind of their uh software engineering
agent. Um and what they do is they
construct agent environments at scale.
Um so you know Swebench is the is the
gold standard of these kinds of things.
And so what they want to do is they want
SWEBench but more. they go out and they
have various automated ways based on
GitHub to generate a ton of different uh
issues and you know given this they want
to basically do RL on these environments
in some ways very unsurprising um and
what do they get they can get sort of RL
performance to go up um one thing I will
say here you know and this is very kind
of important through the the broader
context of what we're talking about you
know the reason why we can sort of put
more and more compute into RL is because
we believe that our reward models are
unhackable or difficult to hack, right?
If that assumption breaks down, your RL
method will find increasingly obscure
ways of cheating you out of your
performance. Um, and so they have this
great plot of um, basically, you know,
in git you can kind of look at future
commits or different commits and if you
have an issue and there's future
commits, you can just kind of look up
what the fix was, right? And this is a
very easy hack for for models to learn.
Um, and so they basically have a whole
reward whose entire purpose it is to
prevent the agent from messing with the
gate history. And if you don't do this,
you end up with a plot that looks like
the right uh where it's learning
learning learning learning learning and
suddenly you get this like kind of
emergent jump where the emergent jump
was actually it learned how to
manipulate the git calls to get sort of
the the history. Um, and in some cases
it can sort of even sort of hack around
certain constraints you give it. Like if
you tell it you can't use git log, you
know, it might add an origin like a
remote and then like query the remote
for uh what happened in certain commits.
So there's all sorts of hacking you can
do. Um, RLVR is only as robust as your
reward. Um, and your rewards can
sometimes be not very robust at all. Um,
you know, as a as a sort of side
comment, you know, one of my students
and I were working on um a project that
was like RL on lean. Lean is this formal
math, you know, verifiable language. Um,
and we naively thought at the time,
there's no way this can go wrong. You
know, lots of people have worked on
lean. The lean compiler is bulletproof.
Turns out the lean compiler is not
adversarially robust. There are sort of
strings that you can put in it that will
allow you to verify proofs that are not
meant to be verified in certain modes.
So, you know, I think the the notion of
verifiable rewards is actually much
trickier than than many of you might
initially think. Um, regardless, you
know, you do this process of
constructing the these GitHub repos at
scale, you go through this process of
doing RL, you know, you see your scores
go up, you know, uh, uh, slow but
steady, and in the end, you will
actually end up getting a system that is
surprisingly good, a model that, you
know, achieves, uh, something like 70.6%
6% on uh SweetBench. Um even though you
have what is basically a really tiny
model, a three billion active parameter
model, you're able to do, you know,
surprisingly well um on these tasks. In
some ways though, I don't know if this
is super surprising. Like RL, of course,
you're going to be able to do well on
the environments for which you've like
kind of trained. You might even get
generalization to your validation set as
you do here. Um, but you always want to
be a little bit careful about comparing
performances. Like task specific
performance doesn't necessarily mean
it'll generalize uh to broader domains.
Okay. Um, so that's basically all I've
got for the RLVR lecture. Um, you know,
remember the the core takeaways of this
lecture, right? Is it's really all about
the reward for RL, right? RLHF and RLVR
arguably they're very similar problems
but you know with the difference being
really just we want more unhackable
rewards so that we can actually put in
much more compute and get these systems
to be much better. Um GRPO at least for
the research community is something that
you know really enabled a lot of this
and you should all know GRPO very well.
You should know you know what the
functional form is and how the updates
are. This is something that you should
know as well as you know uh just
pre-training losses. Um and then finally
at this point you know I think lots of
people know how to do RLVR. Um as you
will find out unfortunately RL remains
very finicky and noisy and it's kind of
painful to work with but it's not that
hard. It's not like you know the old
days of like you doing PO on various
kinds of like really tricky
environments. It's actually a lot
smoother than you might um think. Okay,
I'll stop here for a moment and take any
final questions uh before I let you all
go in case anyone has questions.
>> Or do they play prompting or do they
have different underlying models that
they
>> Right. Yeah. So the question was about
like thinking mode and what's happening
on the back. Um so the interesting thing
about thinking mode really is that it's
actually one model, right? and there's
just like a little prompt tag that
switches them between long and short co
like long coott and no coot almost mode.
Um whereas if you just had like a API
flag or something, you know, that's not
very difficult. Um the fact that they
were putting both of them in together is
kind of the interesting bit there.
>> So you can actually choose not to but
then you add extra prompt yourself to do
coot.
>> Yeah. Or the control mechanism in this
case is in the prompt rather than at the
API or serving layer or something like
that. Yeah. Great.
>> Oh yeah. Um so you mentioned like the
phase of the mid training. I was like
wondering like how much of the
formatting um that goes into the mid
training process like informs what is
able to be learned during the RLVR and
post training and then like as a
secondary to that question. Um if you
don't have like the correct data in mid
training then like is it safe to assume
that the reinforcement learning can't
like sample solution and therefore you
can't learn it?
>> Yeah. So the question was about like the
role of mid training in RL. Um, I think
you know there there are a lot of like
empirical subtleties here like you know
I I don't have like a one-sizefits all
like it'll definitely not work kind of
an answer but to give a little bit of
the nuance I think pre-training and SFT
are doing a lot of the heavy lifting as
long as you have coverage like if
pre-training just doesn't have any code
data then you're in trouble you need mid
training right but if your pre-training
was very diverse and it covered let's
let's go back to the mid-training slide
you know if it covered a lot of stuff
like text code data and it covered a
bunch of like GitHub you data, then this
is very nice to have, but maybe not
critical because you're going to SFT
anyway. And the SFT will allow you to
get close enough to get start getting
some rewards for RL. If you didn't have
SFT, then you know, then you're in deep
trouble, but the fact that we're always
going to be doing some amount of SFT
prels
you. Um, and pre-training has enough
coverage hopefully that you're able to
to get some reasonable generalization.
So, mid-training is very nice to have,
very important in order to get slightly
better generalization. but not
necessarily make or break. I think
>> for model you said there's a step after
train each expert model we're going to
distill uh into a single model again so
does that how does this kind of
distillation work do you kind of have to
design a data mixed
procedure
>> yeah yeah so so that's right like so so
this distillation procedure is going to
require you to write down a sequence of
prompts on which the experts will be
distilling into the final model. Yeah.
Um I can definitely see the advantages
of of this approach which is that you
can have a separate team working on each
expert like it's much easier to like
sort of you know have teams work on this
and then the aggregation could
potentially be simple as well if you
have enough compute. Um it's just that
you know this you know if you have all
the objectives you might as well just
throw it into the big training loop.
Usually I think that's how you would
prefer to do things. That way you don't
have to deal with this distillation
complication. And you could just have
one big training objective that you then
do one you know one training loop.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. So the question was is the long
reasoning training part of mid-training?
Um so I think so there there's long coot
SFT in in both like R1 and uh Kimmy K5
1.1. Um, long coot is not traditionally
part of like mid-training per se, but it
is often like long coott like data is
used in long context extension. So it's
a little bit more subtle like I didn't
talk about long context extension at all
and I regret that. Um, but usually
that's like an additional phase right
before RLHF or other things in this case
also long coot where you sort of extend
the context using any long context data
you have. Usually that's a combination
of like books, code, uh synthetic data
because those are the things that are
long enough to do extension on.
>> Oh yeah. Um so like I guess like related
to this diagram that's currently up. Uh
when you're doing this RO process, let's
say you have like math, chemistry, many
other domains. Um is it common to do it
in parallel one uh I guess like
reinforcement learning training um um
like run or like do you do it
sequentially and if you do it
sequentially like how do you avoid like
forgetting failure?
Yeah, I think the closest answer to this
question of like do you do things
sequentially or in parallel is you know
these kinds of diagrams where um the two
splits that you do is you kind of split
amongst like reasoning problems and
non-reasoning problems and the reasoning
problems all go in one bucket and they
get executed at stage two um and then
sort of the non-reasoning problems kind
of happen at the final RLHF phase um and
this includes stuff like chattiness and
so on and so forth and those all go into
the one later bid which is the the stage
four
Okay, great. Thanks a lot. See you next
week.